<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Realization of Photonic Band Gap Materials and Photonic Heterostructures By Innovative Material Growth]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>376282.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>376282</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070004</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Technical: This project strives for fundamental innovations including: (i) a growth approach to make 3D spiral PBG materials by a glancing-angle-deposition method; (ii) a new design architecture to realize a photonic equivalent of a semiconductor heterostructure using PBG materials; (iii) control of the flow of light at microscopic scales by a photonic heterostructure; (iv) a new scheme of conformal metallic coating to modify the optical properties of a PBG material. A potential outcome of the spiral PBG and photonic heterostructures is diffraction-less control of the flow of light on-chip. The approach is based on thin-film growth of slanted rods at a pre-designed sequence that produces desirable lattice symmetry. This approach is expected to lead to a spatially coherent 3D spiral PBG material without using extensive fabrication tools and it may be scaleable, e.g., up to 6-8 inches. The heterostructure desired has a 3D-2D-3D design that consists of a 2D PBG sandwiched on both sides by 3D PBGs. This combination provides the high photon confinement of a 3D PBG while offering the flexibility and ease of creating functional optical devices (waveguides, bends, filters, cavities) in a 2D PBG material. &lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic research issues in a topical area of electronic/photonic materials science with high technological relevance, and the project represents a balanced research and educational effort. The investigators have an established track record of involving undergraduates and graduates in research, and this will be continued. Such exposure to cutting-edge research instills confidence, creativity and motivation in students. The PI and Co-PIs also have a strong partnership with high school outreach as well as interacting with RPI?s Center for Initiatives in Pre-College Education (CIPCE).&lt;br/&gt;]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0804581</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Toh-Ming</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Toh-Ming Lu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lut@rpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000108472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shawn-Yu</FirstName>
<LastName>Lin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shawn-Yu Lin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sylin@rpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000254316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U5WBFKEBLMX3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01000809DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01000910DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001011DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~125406</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~125427</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~125449</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br /><br /></p> <p><strong>Summary of research results</strong></p> <p>A photonic bandgap (PBG) material, or photonic crystal, is a periodically<br />structured material that interacts strongly with light. This is analogous to<br />the periodic atomic arrangement in solids that interacts strongly with<br />electrons in solids. Electrons in solids, depending on the geometry of the<br />atomic arrangement, can possess different energy levels or bands that control their metallic, magnetic, semiconducting, or insulating properties. In a<br />similar way, by designing different periodic structures, PBG materials can be<br />used to manipulate light for many applications such as light-energy conversion in solar cells and solid-state lighting devices that were not available in the past. Since its origination two decades ago, the PBG material has inspired our imagination as the &ldquo;magic material&rdquo; for new scientific discoveries and innovation. &nbsp;</p> <p>Under this program, we have explored and created a large number of PBG structures by innovative material growth and fabrication:</p> <p><strong><em>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</em></strong><strong><em>Modification of photonic band edge position by high temperature metal coating </em></strong></p> <p>One of the main challenges of achieving a stimulated thermal emission from a<br />three-dimension (3D) PBG material is in high temperature metallic material<br />coating with a nanometer precision. We have developed Iridium (Ir) metal<br />coating using atomic-layer-deposition method, a self-limiting chemisorption<br />process to precisely control the coating thickness. Our data and theoretical<br />calculations indicate a significant improvement in the optical performance of<br />the Ir-coated sample, particularly in moving the PBG band edge toward one<br />micrometer wavelength. This is a landmark wavelength as it would open up<br />exciting possibility of using a silicon solar cell for a highly efficient<br />energy conversion.</p> <p><strong><em>(2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</em></strong><strong><em>Growth of 3D spiral photonic band gap material based on Germanium (Ge)</em></strong></p> <p>The synthesis of a spiral 3D structure is one of the most efficient methods to<br />realize a sub-micrometer size 3D PBG material. However, the main challenge of the spiral growth is in achieving a large, slanted angle (&gt;55-degree) of the<br />arms of the spiral. We have now succeeded in growing a Ge 3D spiral structure with a significantly larger arm angles as compared to that of a silicon<br />spirals. We have also developed a holographic lithography method based on a 3-beam interference effect to make the 2D templates for growing 3D Ge spirals. Using the 2D template, we have successfully realized 3D Ge spiral structures with a slanted angle of 55-degree.</p> <p><strong><em>(3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </em></strong><strong><em>Toward polarized emission: Quantum dots embedded in a 3D photonic band gap material</em></strong></p> <p>Under this program, we studied photon-electron interaction based on the quantum-dots/3D layer-by-layer PBG architecture. We have been successful in realizing the 3D PBG structure and the incorporating quantum-dots (QD) into a 3D PBG structure. We also show that the QD/3DPBG structure is promising in producing an intrinsically polarized light emission. The new 3D PBG architecture consists of a top PBG-layer, a QD-layer, and a bottom PBG-layer. The sample exhibits a polarized, narrow band transmittance of 90% at 1.2 micrometer wavelength. The intensity of the bottom emission is about half as compared to that o the top emission. This preliminary data is encouraging as it indicates that it is likely that the bottom emission contains only one polarization and, therefore, exhibits about half the emission intensity.</p> <p><strong><em>(4)&nbsp;&nbsp;</em></strong><strong><em>Realization of plasmonic filters for multispectral and dual-polarization detection </em></strong></p> <p>One of the long term objectives of this program is to realize 3D photonic band gap (PBG) material at optical wavelength and to mold the flow of light that is not easily achievable by other means. We have succeeded in making a 3D gold PBG material and experimentally show that it supports unique optical modes that are both polarization-sensitive and wavelength-selective. We show that a 5-Layer PBG material can support a p-polarized mode (a singlet) and s-polarized mode (a doublet). One new-degree-of-freedom afforded by our 3D PBG material is that the doublet can be easily tailored by changing the width of the third layer rod.</p> <p><strong>Educational activities</strong></p> <p>Under this program, we have supported a full time Ph.D student to work on the proposed research project. He has successfully defended his thesis in December 2010. The student spent about 60% of his time at RPI's micro-fabrication facility and our nanophotonics optical testing laboratory. He spent about 40% of his time at Cornell's nanofabrication (CNF) laboratory, which was partially funded by NSF and by New York State. At CNF, He has many opportunities interacting with students from Cornell and also from other institutions, making it an exciting learning experience. Additionally, we have also hosted two minority undergraduate students at RPI. One of them has been working on the deposition of slanted rod which is related to the 3D spiral PBG material research supported under this program. The other has been working on computation and electromagnetic-wave modeling of 2D and 3D photonic band gap materials.</p> <p><br /><br /></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2011<br>      Modified by: Toh-Ming&nbsp;Lu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316772863460_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316772863460_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Modification of photonic band edge position by high temperature metal coating"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316772863460_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Modification of photonic band edge position by high temperature metal coating"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Left: a scanning electron micrograph image of a 20 nm Iridium (Ir) coated 3D woodpile photonic bandgap material.  Right: a large shift in Ir coated PBG band edge from a sample with lattice constant of 1.05μm, rod width 0.35μm and rod heigh 0.6μm (1.05-0.35-0.6).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn Lin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Toh-Ming&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Modification of photonic band edge position by high temperature metal coating</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773036648_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773036648_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Growth of 3D Germanium (Ge) spiral photonic band gap material"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773036648_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Growth of 3D Germanium (Ge) spiral photonic band gap material"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Left: a scanning electron micrograph image of the 2 dimensional template fabricated using an optical holographic lithography method. Right: a side view image of the Ge spirals fabricated using an oblique angle deposition technique on the template.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn Lin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Toh-Ming&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Growth of 3D Germanium (Ge) spiral photonic band gap material</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773130816_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773130816_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Quantum dots embedded in a 3D photonic band gap material"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773130816_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Quantum dots embedded in a 3D photonic band gap material"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) A schematic of excitation of a reference quantum dot (QD) sample with no photonic crystal structure; (b) a schematic of excitation of a photonic crystal-QD system; (c) transmission spectrum of the photonic crystal device, indicating the existence of p-mode and s-mode; and (d) the photoluminescen</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn Lin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Toh-Ming&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Quantum dots embedded in a 3D photonic band gap material</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773224602_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773224602_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Realization of plasmonic filters for multispectral and dual-polarization detection"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2011/0804581/0804581_10025189_1316773224602_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Realization of plasmonic filters for multispectral and dual-polarization detection"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) A scanning electron microscope image  of a 5-Layer PBG material that supports a p-polarized mode (singlet in brown color) and s-polarized mode (doublet in blue color). (b) The experimental measurements based on optical transmission indicate either a singlet or doublet transmittance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn Lin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Toh-Ming&nbsp;Lu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Realization of plasmonic filters for multispectral and dual-polarization detection</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     Summary of research results  A photonic bandgap (PBG) material, or photonic crystal, is a periodically structured material that interacts strongly with light. This is analogous to the periodic atomic arrangement in solids that interacts strongly with electrons in solids. Electrons in solids, depending on the geometry of the atomic arrangement, can possess different energy levels or bands that control their metallic, magnetic, semiconducting, or insulating properties. In a similar way, by designing different periodic structures, PBG materials can be used to manipulate light for many applications such as light-energy conversion in solar cells and solid-state lighting devices that were not available in the past. Since its origination two decades ago, the PBG material has inspired our imagination as the "magic material" for new scientific discoveries and innovation.    Under this program, we have explored and created a large number of PBG structures by innovative material growth and fabrication:  (1)        Modification of photonic band edge position by high temperature metal coating   One of the main challenges of achieving a stimulated thermal emission from a three-dimension (3D) PBG material is in high temperature metallic material coating with a nanometer precision. We have developed Iridium (Ir) metal coating using atomic-layer-deposition method, a self-limiting chemisorption process to precisely control the coating thickness. Our data and theoretical calculations indicate a significant improvement in the optical performance of the Ir-coated sample, particularly in moving the PBG band edge toward one micrometer wavelength. This is a landmark wavelength as it would open up exciting possibility of using a silicon solar cell for a highly efficient energy conversion.  (2)   Growth of 3D spiral photonic band gap material based on Germanium (Ge)  The synthesis of a spiral 3D structure is one of the most efficient methods to realize a sub-micrometer size 3D PBG material. However, the main challenge of the spiral growth is in achieving a large, slanted angle (&gt;55-degree) of the arms of the spiral. We have now succeeded in growing a Ge 3D spiral structure with a significantly larger arm angles as compared to that of a silicon spirals. We have also developed a holographic lithography method based on a 3-beam interference effect to make the 2D templates for growing 3D Ge spirals. Using the 2D template, we have successfully realized 3D Ge spiral structures with a slanted angle of 55-degree.  (3)      Toward polarized emission: Quantum dots embedded in a 3D photonic band gap material  Under this program, we studied photon-electron interaction based on the quantum-dots/3D layer-by-layer PBG architecture. We have been successful in realizing the 3D PBG structure and the incorporating quantum-dots (QD) into a 3D PBG structure. We also show that the QD/3DPBG structure is promising in producing an intrinsically polarized light emission. The new 3D PBG architecture consists of a top PBG-layer, a QD-layer, and a bottom PBG-layer. The sample exhibits a polarized, narrow band transmittance of 90% at 1.2 micrometer wavelength. The intensity of the bottom emission is about half as compared to that o the top emission. This preliminary data is encouraging as it indicates that it is likely that the bottom emission contains only one polarization and, therefore, exhibits about half the emission intensity.  (4)  Realization of plasmonic filters for multispectral and dual-polarization detection   One of the long term objectives of this program is to realize 3D photonic band gap (PBG) material at optical wavelength and to mold the flow of light that is not easily achievable by other means. We have succeeded in making a 3D gold PBG material and experimentally show that it supports unique optical modes that are both polarization-sensitive and wavelength-selective. We show that a 5-Layer PBG material can support a p-polarized mode (a singlet) and s-polarized mode (a doublet). One new-degree-of-freedom afforded by our 3D PBG material is that the doublet can be easily tailored by changing the width of the third layer rod.  Educational activities  Under this program, we have supported a full time Ph.D student to work on the proposed research project. He has successfully defended his thesis in December 2010. The student spent about 60% of his time at RPI's micro-fabrication facility and our nanophotonics optical testing laboratory. He spent about 40% of his time at Cornell's nanofabrication (CNF) laboratory, which was partially funded by NSF and by New York State. At CNF, He has many opportunities interacting with students from Cornell and also from other institutions, making it an exciting learning experience. Additionally, we have also hosted two minority undergraduate students at RPI. One of them has been working on the deposition of slanted rod which is related to the 3D spiral PBG material research supported under this program. The other has been working on computation and electromagnetic-wave modeling of 2D and 3D photonic band gap materials.              Last Modified: 09/23/2011       Submitted by: Toh-Ming Lu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
