<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SGER: Dam removal and the response of gravel-bed rivers to sediment pulses]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29923.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29923</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Cutler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pcutler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924961</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This study will investigate sediment transport and channel evolution in gravel-bed rivers&lt;br/&gt;in response to sediment pulses, taking advantage of the field-scale experiment that will be&lt;br/&gt;created by the removal of Milltown Dam on the Clark Fork of the Columbia River, MT. Through&lt;br/&gt;data collection on pre- and post-dam removal channel conditions and on bedload and suspended&lt;br/&gt;load transport out of Milltown reservoir during high flow periods, this research will address&lt;br/&gt;fundamental questions about fluvial processes, sediment transport and deposition, and dam&lt;br/&gt;removal. Several hypotheses will be investigated about how pulses of fine sediment infiltrate&lt;br/&gt;into and affect the mobility of armored river beds, about spatial and temporal patterns of&lt;br/&gt;sediment transport and deposition, and about effective discharges for transporting sediment&lt;br/&gt;pulses. This research will provide an excellent opportunity to evaluate how previous flume&lt;br/&gt;research or field studies of small channels, upon which much of what is known about sediment&lt;br/&gt;transport and related aspects of fluvial processes is based, scale up to larger rivers. The&lt;br/&gt;data collected here will also be evaluated in the context of the implications of geomorphic&lt;br/&gt;responses and sediment geochemistry for habitat and biological processes.&lt;br/&gt;Removal of Milltown Dam, which will begin in spring 2008 and continue the following winter,&lt;br/&gt;is especially notable because (1) it is the largest dam removal to date in the United States&lt;br/&gt;in terms of the volume of reservoir sediment potentially available for downstream transport&lt;br/&gt;(approximately 3 million m3; another 2 million m3 are being mechanically removed); (2) the&lt;br/&gt;dam is the downstream end of the largest Superfund site in the United States, the Clark Fork&lt;br/&gt;Complex, and reservoir sediments are composed largely of contaminated mine tailings; (3) it&lt;br/&gt;is occurring on a regionally important river that includes designated Critical Habitat for&lt;br/&gt;bull trout, a federally threatened species. Systematic study of this dam removal will therefore&lt;br/&gt;have broader impacts on multiple levels, including for understanding the sediment and metals&lt;br/&gt;transport associated with a significant dam removal, for the insights it lends to upcoming&lt;br/&gt;planned removals of large dams, and for its broader contribution to understanding how gravel-bed&lt;br/&gt;rivers respond to increased sediment fluxes. Broader impacts will also derive from the project?s&lt;br/&gt;interdisciplinary nature, whereby analyses of geomorphic processes, geochemistry, hydrology,&lt;br/&gt;and fish response will be combined to understand downstream effects of dam removal.&lt;br/&gt;This project will help a new faculty member build a research program in fluvial geomorphic&lt;br/&gt;processes and will directly support one graduate and one undergraduate student. The project&lt;br/&gt;will also foster ongoing collaboration efforts between University of Montana and Salish-Kootenai&lt;br/&gt;College, a tribal college in Pablo, MT, whose students will assist field data collection and&lt;br/&gt;analysis under the guidance of the PI. Further, data collection and analysis related to Milltown&lt;br/&gt;Dam removal will be incorporated into graduate and undergraduate geomorphology and geochemistry&lt;br/&gt;courses, an integration of teaching and research that will be facilitated by the project?s&lt;br/&gt;close proximity to the University of Montana.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0809082</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilcox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew C Wilcox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andrew.wilcox@umontana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000082022</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Montana</Name>
<CityName>MISSOULA</CityName>
<ZipCode>598120003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4062436670</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>32 CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DAY7Z8ZD48Q3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MONTANA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Montana]]></Name>
<CityName>MISSOULA</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>598120003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[32 CAMPUS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01000809DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~29923</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
