<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Community College Undergraduate Research:  A Model of Integration]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>493995.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>493995</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Lee S. Ledbetter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Biological Sciences (61). "Community College Undergraduate Research: Building a Model of Integration" involves the design, implementation and evaluation of a model for integrating undergraduate research into a community college science curriculum. The project involves the use of scientific principles contained within a portfolio of ongoing research programs to develop inquiry-based educational materials (such as problem-based learning modules and case studies) for freshman biology courses. These materials are then being expanded into an undergraduate research experience within a credit-bearing, transferable, advanced sophomore-level course. The sophomore-level course curriculum includes training students as peer-leaders to support the development of new student projects emerging from the freshman courses and supports the creation of an educational environment where research and education are integrated. The project involves a collaboration of five community colleges, one four-year school, four environmental research organizations, and a state government agency.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed project lies in establishing an adoptable model that supports community college efforts to shift to inquiry-based and project-based coursework, to get community college students engaged in undergraduate research, and to make connections to four-year college science programs and their undergraduate research efforts. The project addresses many of the barriers associated with conducting undergraduate research at the community college level. Project evaluation is using a variety of approaches to address the success of the project in achieving its major objectives, which include improving student learning, increasing the involvement of both faculty and students in research, increasing the use of inquiry-based approaches by participating faculty, and increasing the level of interaction between the faculty at the participating community colleges and four-year institutions.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposal include its strong focus on improving the quality of science education at the community college level, where there are disproportionate number of students from underrepresented groups; the establishment of a network of community college faculty dedicated to project-based learning and undergraduate research; and an increase in the capacity of community colleges to prepare future scientists with the skills necessary to conduct scientific research. Plans for dissemination of project results include presentations and workshops at national meetings and student presentations at local and regional conferences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0816515</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hewlett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Hewlett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hewletja@flcc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000157723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Finger Lakes Community College</Name>
<CityName>CANANDAIGUA</CityName>
<ZipCode>144248405</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5857851206</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3325 MARVIN SANDS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RHAVTVGK6GX8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FINGER LAKES COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>RHAVTVGK6GX8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Finger Lakes Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>CANANDAIGUA</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>144248405</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3325 MARVIN SANDS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7492</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04000809DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>1300CYXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>045176</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~493995</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
