<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research:  Improving the Geoscience Major:  Developing Community Expertise in Curriculum Design and Assessment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25440.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25440</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Matty</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Geosciences (42) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;From a student point of view, the ultimate goal of an undergraduate experience is the completion of a major - an integrated course of study in a specific discipline. Curricular aspects of the major are enhanced by departmentally focused co-curricular elements including research experiences, community service, and informal social interactions that together constitute the undergraduate program. While programs should vary between institutions in response to institutional mission, student population, faculty expertise, and local resources, programs could be strengthened substantially through the application of educational research and the sharing of expertise among the geoscience community. This project is grounded in previous work defining characteristics of thriving departments. It enhances the design and implementation of geoscience curricula and programs using three workshop strategies: 1) a topical workshop focused on a single issue facing departments - in this case strategies for evaluating departmental programs; 2) a dissemination workshop for departmental teams showcasing successful strategies for addressing a range of issues; and a 3) a visiting workshop program, offered in collaboration with the National Association of Geoscience Teachers Distinguished Speaker Program, that brings experienced leaders and a customized program to a specific department. The web resources developed in association with the workshops support further dissemination of existing strategies for strengthening departments. The evaluation plan uses a longitudinal design to measure impact on departmental programming on timescales from six months to two years and is designed to determine the relative impact of the three models on the ability of the departments to strengthen their programming. This effort will produce a tested model for conducting national and/or regional workshops and related supporting activities that help departments address important issues identified as impediments to building a stronger department. This program addresses the challenges faced in building strong geoscience departments. In addition, it seeks to provide support for enhancing the ability of departments to review or evaluate their departmental programs and build skill in effective program assessment. This skill is both underdeveloped in the geoscience community and critical to the collection of data needed to understand the impact of various aspects of departmental programs as well as the entire curriculum on student learning for all types of students.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0817265</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>P. Geoffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Feiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>P. Geoffrey Feiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pgfeis@wm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000089197</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>R</FirstName>
<LastName>Macdonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>R H Macdonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rhmacd@wm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000418539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of William and Mary</Name>
<CityName>WILLIAMSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>231852817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7572213965</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1314 S MOUNT VERNON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EVWJPCY6AD97</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLLEGE OF WILLIAM AND MARY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of William and Mary]]></Name>
<CityName>WILLIAMSBURG</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>231852817</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1314 S MOUNT VERNON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7492</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04000809DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>1300CYXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[H-1B FUND, EDU, NSF]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>045176</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~25440</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
