<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Examining Race and Ownership Status in Long-time Businesses and Organizations? Reactions to Gentrification]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>104160</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[PI: Daniel Monroe Sullivan, Ph.D., Department of Sociology, Portland State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Examining Race and Ownership Status in Long-time Businesses and Organizations? Reactions to Gentrification&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project will collect data from 80 interviews in two racially diverse, gentrifying neighborhoods in Portland, Oregon to examine the linkages between race and ownership in explaining gentrification outcomes.  Gentrification, the process of wealthier residents moving into a poorer neighborhood in sufficient numbers to transform its social identity, is occurring in parts of many U.S. cities. Often gentrification is characterized by whites moving into predominantly black neighborhoods, resulting?at least for a time?in racially diverse neighborhoods.  The main goal of this project is to examine neighborhood racial integration by analyzing how long-time businesses and organizations react to gentrification in their neighborhood, in terms of whether they continue to operate in their neighborhood (thus facilitating stable racial integration) and whether newcomers become involved in their business/ organization, as workers or customers (thus facilitating genuine social integration). The central hypothesis is that, among long-time predominantly black businesses/ organizations, those that own their own building are more likely to stay in the neighborhood and socially integrate with newcomers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The interviews will complement a recent survey of 164 businesses/organizations that will be selected from a list of survey respondents.  All will have operated in their neighborhood since before gentrification began and they will correspond to one of four categories: black-owned, white-owned, black renters, and white renters. Interviewer and interviewee will be matched based on race. This research will make both scholarly and policy contributions. In terms of scholarly contribution, it will examine whether long-time businesses/organizations? reactions to newcomers are based more on cultural characteristics or on economic interests. Researchers who emphasize the importance of culture argue that differences in racial identity and socioeconomic status create divisions between newcomers and long-time businesses/organizations, making it difficult to achieve racial stability and social integration. However, researchers who emphasize the importance of economics argue that businesses/organizations benefit financially from gentrification and therefore, regardless of cultural differences, those that own their building are more likely to stay in the neighborhood and be more open to newcomers than those that rent. This study also has important policy implications for it may be that ownership serves three important functions in racially integrated, gentrifying neighborhoods: (1) securing affordable space for long-time businesses/organizations, including predominantly black ones, (2) maintaining stable neighborhood integration, and (3) increasing social integration. The broader impacts of this study of integrated neighborhoods will generate a greater understanding of pathways out of racial segregation, including understanding whether ownership facilitates stable racial integration and inter-racial social integration.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0817941</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Sullivan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dsulliva@pdx.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000336698</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Portland State University</Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>972015522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 SW 4TH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H4CAHK2RD945</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H4CAHK2RD945</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Portland State University]]></Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972015522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 SW 4TH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01000809DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01000910DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~24160</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
