<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI:  Acquisition of Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption Ionization and Electrospray Ionization Mass Spectrometers for the Analysis of New Synthetic Polymers and Materials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>788600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>788600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070006</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas P. Rieker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization (MALDI) and electrospray ionization (ESI) mass spectrometers will be acquired for the analysis of synthetic, macromolecular materials.  The instruments will support a variety of interdisciplinary research programs in polymer science and engineering at the University of Akron, which focus on the creation of new polymers and materials and the examination of these substances for specific applications.  The studies performed within this research regularly raise questions about the mass, composition, functional groups, purity, connectivity, and architecture of functionalized oligomers and macromonomers, hyperbranched and dendritic systems, organic and inorganic polymers, copolymers, polymer interfaces, and polymer-biomolecule conjugates.  These questions can be answered with exceptional sensitivity and specificity by combined MALDI time-of-flight and ESI ion trap / time-of-flight mass spectrometry analyses.  The high resolution, high mass accuracy, and tandem mass spectrometry capabilities of the instruments to be obtained will significantly facilitate the desired structural characterizations, fostering the development of new methods of polymerization and the discovery of new materials with properties fine-tuned for particular technological uses, inter alia, in photovoltaic devices, sensors, or drug delivery systems.  The instruments will be accessible to industrial researchers and college faculty from Northeast Ohio, who need ESI or MALDI mass spectrometry to solve their analytical problems.  They will also be available for a variety of educational activities, including instrumental analysis courses and research courses for graduate, undergraduate, REU, and McNair students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Akron (UA) will purchase instruments to study structure and enhance research and education in many interconnected research projects in polymer science and engineering.  Currently, researchers at UA focus on the preparation of new materials; on the mechanical, physical, and chemical properties of these materials; and on the optimization of their properties for specific applications in nanotechnology and biomedical fields.  For example, materials for light harvesting devices, biosensors, stents, implants, and drug delivery systems are being studied.  The research naturally leads to questions about the chemical make-up, size, and purity of the materials.  The mass spectrometry equipment requested will enable rapid and accurate measurement of these properties and lead to the making of new materials.  The problem solving capability of the instruments will make the discovery of new materials easier and allow the properties of the materials to be fine-tuned for the desired use.  The instruments will be used by academic and industrial researchers within the Ohio Mass Spectrometry Consortium (universities, other research institutions, and affiliated industrial corporations) as well as by college faculty from universities in Northeast Ohio.  The instruments will also be available for a variety of educational activities, including undergraduate courses in instrumental analysis and research courses for graduate and undergraduate students.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0821313</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Newkome</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George R Newkome</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gnewkome@uakron.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000280138</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roderic</FirstName>
<LastName>Quirk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roderic P Quirk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rpquirk@uakron.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000331637</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen Z.</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Z. D Cheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scheng@uakron.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000131777</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chrys</FirstName>
<LastName>Wesdemiotis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chrys Wesdemiotis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wesdemiotis@uakron.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000124084</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Akron</Name>
<CityName>AKRON</CityName>
<ZipCode>443250002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3309722760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>302 BUCHTEL COMMON</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DFNLDECWM8J8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF AKRON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>DFNLDECWM8J8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Akron]]></Name>
<CityName>AKRON</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>443250002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[302 BUCHTEL COMMON]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01000809DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~788600</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
