<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Exploring Factors in the Social Ecology of the Home that Affect First-Grade Girls' Spatial Skills and Early Math Strategies]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499681.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499681</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jolene Jesse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjesse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927303</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Intellectual Merit: In the present study, researchers from the Applied Developmental and Educational Psychology program at Boston College plan to investigate the role of the home environment in the formation of girls' spatial reasoning skills, and their ability to apply effective strategies for solving math problems. This primary context for early development provides the initial building blocks for the acquisition of spatial skills important to later math and science. Yet, despite a long history of empirical and theoretical work on the home as a major context of learning and development, there have been few studies exploring the importance of this environment for girls' early spatial and math development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is an extensive body of research showing that males have an advantage over females on spatial reasoning skills relating to the ability to use mental imagery and manipulation of images as a way of solving problems. This gender difference has been documented as early as ages 4-6, and thus, is present prior to formal schooling. Furthermore, for girls in particular, these types of spatial reasoning skills are linked to math performance. Yet, little is known about elements of the home environment that might support the growth of girls' spatial reasoning skills. This present study is designed to contribute to the understanding of how variations in early home environments link to young girls' spatial and math performance in school. This research has the potential to shift the perspective regarding later challenges that girls experience in math and science; intervening early to develop girls' spatial reasoning skills has potential to impact both their later math skills and their math self-confidence.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;School spatial and math assessments, parent interviews, and home observations will be conducted with first-grade girls in the Boston area. The central goal of the study is to identify the developmental consequences of both general learning supports and math- and spatial-specific experiences available to young girls in their homes. As an important component of this, girls living in families representing a range of income levels, from poor to affluent, will be studied. Both the range and developmental impact of girls' experiences in their homes will likely vary as a function of economic constraints on families. The questions addressed in the study include: (1) What elements of young girls' home environments predict their spatial skills, as well as the strategies they use for math problem solving? (2) Do girls' spatial skills mediate links between home environments and math strategies? (3) Do these direct and indirect (i.e., mediated) relationships differ for girls as a function of family economic status? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact : The major emphasis in gender and mathematics has been on attitudinal factors and on ways of increasing girls' and women's participation in math and science, with relatively less focus on girls' cognitive and academic skills. Yet, if girls on average start out in school with an early disadvantage in developing specific cognitive skills and strategies, this may contribute to later difficulties in mathematics and science, as well as engendering a lack of self-confidence and interest in approaching STEM content. This research has the potential to reveal critical early experiences that enable some young girls to form effective spatial reasoning skills and apply these skills to mathematics problem solving. Understanding these influences will help target future efforts to promote school readiness in mathematics, so that girls may take full advantage of spatial thinking as a tool for solving math problems.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0827155</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beth</FirstName>
<LastName>Casey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beth Casey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[caseyb@bc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000303990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Dearing</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Dearing</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dearinge@bc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000118790</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>CHESTNUT HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJ3JH8CRJBZ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>CHESTNUT HILL</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 COMMONWEALTH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1544</Code>
<Text>RES ON GENDER IN SCI &amp; ENGINE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~499681</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
